<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Arrest de la cour de Parlement. Les Princes, et toutes les chambres assemblees, le 22 Aoust 1652. Pour remercier le Roy de Lèsloignement de Cardinal Marzarin, &amp; supplier sa Majesté retourner dans sa bonne ville de Paris; &amp; de rendre le calme à son estat. Avec la declaration de Messieurs les Princes.</title>
            <author>France. Parlement (Paris)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74875</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E674_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207197</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866266</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866266</idno>
            <idno type="VID">166274</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74875)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 166274)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 103:E674[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Arrest de la cour de Parlement. Les Princes, et toutes les chambres assemblees, le 22 Aoust 1652. Pour remercier le Roy de Lèsloignement de Cardinal Marzarin, &amp; supplier sa Majesté retourner dans sa bonne ville de Paris; &amp; de rendre le calme à son estat. Avec la declaration de Messieurs les Princes.</title>
                  <author>France. Parlement (Paris)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Suivant la copie imprimée à Paris, Chez Jacob Chevalier, pres̀ Saint Iean de Latran. Et r'imprimée à la Haye, chez Samuel Broun, Libraire Anglois sur la grand sale de la cour,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[The Hague] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno M. DC. LIII. [1652]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Louis the XIV removed Cardinal Mazarin from office August 19, 1652.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mazarin, Jules, 1602-1661.</term>
               <term>Fronde --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIV, 1643-1715 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="fre">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:166274:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 22 -->
            <p>ARREST DE LA COUR <hi>DE</hi> PARLEMENT.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LES PRINCES,</hi> Et toutes les Chambres aſſemblées, le 22 Aouſt 1652.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pour remercier le Roy de l'eſloignement du Cardinal Mazarin, &amp; ſupplier ſa Majeſté de retourner dans ſa bonne Ville de Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris; &amp; de rendre le calme à ſon Eſtat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AVEC LA DECLARATION De Meſſieurs les <hi>PRINCES.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Suivant la Copie Imprimée</hi> à PARIS, Chez <hi>Jacob Chevalier,</hi> prés Saint Iean de Latran.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Et r' Imprimée à la HAYE,</hi> Chez SAMUEL BROUN, Libraire Anglois ſur la Grand Sale de la Cour. Anno M.DC.LII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:166274:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 23 -->
            <head>Extrait des Regiſtres de Parlement.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>E jour la Cour les Chambres aſſemblées en preſence de Belchefer Subſtitud pour le Procureur General du Roy Monſieur le Duc d'Orleans, &amp; apres luy le ſieur Prince de Condé ont dit qu'ils avoyent aſſez fait cognoiſtre de vive voix &amp; par leurs Declarations faites en la Cour que le ſujet pour lequel ils avoyent pris les armes, n'eſtoit que pour l'eſloigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment du Cardinal Mazarin hors le Royaume. Que ſur les advis à eux donnez ils apportoyent à la Cour leurs Declarations ſignées, continue en ces termes:</p>
            <p>LA Reſolution qu'a pris le Roy de faire ſortir le Cardinal Maza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin hors du Royaume, dans la conjoncture preſente, juſtifie d'une telle ſorte ce que nous avons fait pour l'empeſcher d'y r'en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trer: Et depuis qu'il y eſt de retour, pour le faire ſortir, que per ſonne ne peut plus blaſmer noſtre conduite avec raiſon. Auſſi ceux qui ont voulu authoriſer ſa demeurer en France n'ont-ils eu la har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieſſe d'alleguer autre choſe ſmon qu'il n'eſtoit que le pretexte de la guerre, &amp; qu'elle avoit des cauſes que ſon eſloignement ne ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roit pas capable d'oſter: Mais comme nous proteſtons qu'il a eſté le ſeul &amp; veritable motif que nous a mis les armes à la main. Nous venons dans la Compagnie pour l'aſſeurer que nous ſommes preſts de les poſer &amp;c d'executer ſincerement les Declarations que nous y avons faites, preſupoſant que ſa ſortie hors du Royaume ſoit ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective: Et pourveu qu'il plaiſe à ſa Majeſté de faire ce qu'il con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient pour le repos de ſon Eſtat. Et ce qui s'eſt touſiours pratiqué en de ſemblables occaſions qui conſiſte ſeulement à donner une Amniſtie Generale en bonne forme, &amp; eſloigner les troupes des
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:166274:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 23 -->
environs de Paris, &amp; retirer celles qui ſont dans la Guyenne &amp; lans les Provinces, pour les empeſcher allieurs ſur les Frontieres: Et à reſtablir les choſes au meſme eſtat qu'elles étoyent avant les preſens mouvemens, &amp; particulierement ce qui concerne la re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union du Parlement, &amp; donner une route &amp; ſeureté pour la re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traite des trouppes eſtrangeres qui ſont ſous noſtre Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Nous ſommes tous diſpoſez à envoyer exprés à ſa Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſté pour luy faire entendre les meſmes choſes avec tout le reſpect que Nous luy devons, ne doutant point que la Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagnie ne le juge ainſi à propos, &amp; de Nous conformer aux ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timens qu'elle prendra dans une occaſion auſſi importante qu'eſt celle-cy, &amp; d'où deſpend la tranquillité publique. En teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moing dequoy Nous avons ſigné la preſente Declaration. Ladite Declaration leve, ouy ſur ce ledit Subſtitud, qui a dit que c'eſt par une exuberance de bonté &amp; affection que Monſieur Duc d'Orleans &amp; Monſieur le Prince ont voulu reïterer verballement, &amp; par eſcrit les meſmes Declarations qui ont eſté cy-devant par eux fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes en ce lieu, ſans qu'il en fut beſoin, parce que des la premiere fois qu'elles y ont eſté faites il n'y a perſonne qui n'ait perſuadé qu'elles ne fuiſſent entierement ſinceres &amp; mieux eſcrites &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignées dans leur coeur tout Royal que dans le Regiſtre de la Cour: mais puis qu'ils teſmoignoyent tant de bonne volonté pour le bien &amp; le ſalut de l'Eſtat &amp; pour cette Compagnie qu'il eſtoit encore neceſſaire de les ſupplier de s'employer vers le Roy pour moyen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſon retour en cette ville de Paris pour l'honnorer &amp; conſerver par ſa preſence, &amp; de la part de la Cour, le Roy ayant deſia par ſa bonté fait la premiere démarche pour luy faire reſſentir ſes gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, La Compagnie eſtoit obligée de faire tout ce qu'elle ſcauroit eſtre agreable au Roy pour repondre à ſes volontez &amp; luy teſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>igner avec quelle affection l'on luy veut rendre les ſubmiſſions &amp; obeiſſances qu'il peut deſirer, &amp; pour cét effet il luy ſemble eſtre expedient de deputer pour aller vers le Roy le remercier tres-humblement de ce qu'il a eu eſgard aux remonſtrances de ſon Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement, Que s'il s'eſt paſsé quelque choſe qui luy ait pû deplaire,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:166274:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 24 -->
le ſupplier d'oublier, &amp; aſſeurer des bonnes intentions de la Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagnie, luy faire pareille ſupplication de retourner dans Paris pour aſſe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rer les peuples &amp; eſtouffer toutes les deffiances qui ſe ſont formées de part &amp; autre pour formenter les diviſions. Si la Cour trouve bon d'adjouſter que la Garde des portes ſoit levée, &amp; ceſſer la levée des taxes qui ont eſté impoſées, ce ſera choſe agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able au Roy, &amp; que la deliberation ſoit portée par tels de Meſſieurs qu'il plaira à la Cour deputer apres que l'on aura ſceu que le Roy trouvera bon de les ouïr.</p>
            <p>LADITE COUR a arreſté &amp; ordonné que le Roy ſera tres-humblement remercié par deputez d'icelle de ce qu'il luy a pleu accorder l'eſloignement dudit Cardinal Mazarin, Que les Compagnies ſouveraines &amp; les Corps de la ville ſeront advertis &amp; conviez de faire meſme deputation, ſupplier ledit Seigneur Roy de revenir à Paris, &amp; l'aſſeurer de tous devoirs, reſpects, ſoubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, &amp; obeiſſances, de ſes Officiers &amp; ſujets. Que ledit ſieur Duc d'Orleans, &amp; ledit ſieur Prince ſeront auſſi remerciez de leur bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne volonté, priez de continuer leur affection pour la paix du Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yaume, &amp; d'envoyer inceſſamment, &amp; au pluſtoſt qu'il ſe pourra pardevers ſa Majeſté pour parachever ce qui eſt neceſſaire au bien &amp; repos de l'eſtat, &amp; a cette fin demeurera ladite De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration au Greffe de ladite Cour. Fait en Parlement le 22. jour du mois d'Aouſt mil ſix cens cinquantedeux.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Signé, <hi>DU TILLET.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
